Finding Aid for Student Advocacy Center of Michigan records, 1975-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Student Advocacy Center of Michigan records 1975-2004
Student Advocacy Center of Michigan.
04125 Bh 2
The Students Advocacy Center of Michigan (SAC), established in 1975 in Ann Arbor, was the only organization in Michigan, providing non-legal advocacy to students and their parents who were eligible for general and special public education programs. SAC was involved in numerous controversies involving public school policies and practices. Ruth Zweifler, founding member and director, led SAC and built a statewide presence through activism for students and parents. The record group includes administrative files and other subject files of executive director Ruth Zweifler documenting the Center's advocacy programs, its management and funding sources; includes clippings relating to the Center's support in 1979 of Ann Arbor teachers having training in Black English.
6 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records (donor no. 9517 ) were transferred to the Bentley Historical Library in 2004. Additional records have been received.
The record group is open to research.
Beginning as a volunteer tutor in Angell School, 1969-1975, Ruth Zweifler led a group of concerned citizens to form the Student Advocacy Center (SAC). Established in 1975, the Student Advocacy Center provided advocacy services for individual public school students and their families to relieve school-related problems and monitored local and state educational agencies for policies and practices that hurt children. Issues focused on school exclusions, such as, drop-out, "push-out," suspension, and expulsion. SAC concerned itself with the relationship between academic competency and exclusion. Finally, SAC attempted to identify support services and strategies to enhance school success for marginal students.
The by laws and mission statement of SAC went through several revisions after 1975. The SAC has as its current mission statement (May 5, 2001), "Student Advocacy Center of Michigan operates with the conviction that a vigorous public school system that serves all children well is an essential component of a robust democracy. Toward that end the Student Advocacy Center of Michigan advocates on behalf of, and in partnership with, Michigan's children and young adults and their families in order to ensure that those who are educationally unserved, underserved or ill-served receive a free, individualized and equitable education and become fully participating members of their communities."
SAC took an interventionist approach on the behalf of identified students. The landmark case that brought SAC into the national spotlight was the 1979 case in the court of Judge Charles Joiner in Ann Arbor. A group of African-American parents, with the support of SAC, sued the Ann Arbor Board of Education on the issue of Black English classroom instruction for their children. The suit was resolved in favor of the parents and the Ann Arbor Board of Education was compelled to provide accommodation to African-American students.
Initially, SAC acted as advocate for Ann Arbor area students and their parents, but in 1988 (Ann Arbor News, December, 18, 1988), the volunteer group reorganized on a statewide basis with a board of directors, enlarged to thirty members, and a new advisory board. At this time, SAC expanded its focus from individuals to issues on a statewide basis. Up to this point SAC had operated on an annual budget of about $15,000. By broadening the geographic base through board members, SAC hoped to expand its finances as well.
In 1998, SAC undertook a data gathering project on public school expulsions, contacting school districts directly with requests for information under the Freedom of Information Act (FOIA). The resulting report, "Access Denied, "established that 571 children were expelled from 17 of the state's 554 school districts in a two-year period. A FOIA request from SAC to the State of Michigan revealed that data on expulsions statewide did not exist. By conducting an analysis of the SAC case files for 1999-2000, SAC concluded that 71% of expelled students for that period were either Special Education certified, receiving section 504 protections, or had exhibited identifiable risk factors prior to expulsion. These conclusions were used as a basis for expansion of interventions that SAC promoted. In 1999, a Lawyers Committee was created. The Lawyers' Committee set as goals: to demand accurate information about the number and reasons for student expulsions from Michigan public schools, to "spread the word" about the negative effects of student expulsions, and to actively engage state legislators. This committee was composed of attorneys across Michigan who served voluntarily to review state legislation that negatively impacted public school students' right to an education and to advocate legislative change. An Attorney Network was also formed to provide pro bono assistance to cases referred by SAC if a student problem was beyond the SAC mission. At this time SAC created a website as a resource for parents or students who need to know the procedures for initiating intervention and the free resources available to them. The website was developed through a cooperative effort with Washtenaw Community College.
In 1999, Project SOAR was developed and funded to provide educational alternatives to expelled public school students. From SOAR the Washtenaw County Intermediate School District spun off another program, School to Youth: Learning for Unserved Students (STYLUS). Ken Ludwig, SOAR case manager, provided services to more than half of STYLUS participants. After a Board revitalization effort in 2000, SAC made a successful effort to submit and obtain grants for several programs, implemented in 2001: Active Voices of Youth and Raise a Strong Voice for Children. Active Voices of Youth, funded by the W. K. Kellogg Foundation with $32,000, enabled SAC to organize high school student focus groups from schools around Michigan to form planning groups with the purpose of creating positive school climates. Raise a Strong Voice for Youth Legal Advocacy Project, a partnership with the University of Michigan Law School, and funded by the Michigan State Bar Foundation, strengthened SAC personnel with the creation of a staff attorney position and brought legal and social work volunteer professionals into SAC staff.
Fire destroyed SAC offices February 19, 2002 when an arsonist set fire to the United Way Building where SAC was a tenant. It is important to note that many of the SAC files were destroyed in the fire, so there are many gaps in these records.
The Student Advocacy Center of Michigan records include administrative files and other subject files of executive director Ruth Zweifler documenting the Center’s advocacy programs, its management and funding sources. Also included are clippings relating to the Center’s support in 1979 of Ann Arbor teachers having training in Black English. The records are arranged into six series: Administration; Ruth Zweifler, Executive Director, 1975-2004; Program; Grants and Fundraising, Digital Materials, and Audiovisual Materials
Subjects:
Student Advocacy Center of Michigan.; Black English--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Children with social disabilities--Education--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Children with social disabilities--Education--Michigan.; Education--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Education--Michigan.; School discipline--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; School discipline--Michigan.; Schools--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Schools--Michigan.
Contributors:
Zweifler, Ruth.
- Administration
  The Administration series contains seven subseries. The Board of Directors subseries includes SAC corporate papers, minutes for 1988-1991 and 1999-2001, strategic plans, and the 2000-2001 Board revitalization process. The Clippings subseries highlight SAC activities in the public eye through the three decades of existence and is a primary source for finding details on SAC activities in Ann Arbor and around the state. Included in this subseries are the contents of a scrapbook of newspaper clippings, damaged by the 2002 fire, documenting the Black History case. This case received national attention and was cited in the New York Times and other major newspapers. The Office Management subseries contains general information used for the public relations and partial information on fundraising activities. No budgetary information was available in the records as accessioned. The Publications subseries includes the SAC newsletter, "Active Voice" from 1975 to 2002. There is also a copy of "The Fourth 'R', Student Rights, A Handbook for Michigan Public School Students and Their Families," an article entitled "Access Denied," and two relevant articles that appeared in the Administrative Law Quarterly.
  - Board of Directors
    - Agendas 1998-2004 (Box 1)
    - Annual Report 1998 (Box 1)
    - Corporate papers
      - Articles of Incorporation (Box 1)
      - By Laws (Box 1)
      - Mission Statement (Box 1)
    - Members and Committees 2002-2004 (Box 1)
    - Minutes
      - 1988-1991 (Box 1)
      - 1999-2001 (Box 1)
    - Reports Submitted to Board of Directors (Box 1)
    - Revitalization 2000-2001 (Box 1)
    - Strategic plan 1995, 1999 (Box 1)
  - Clippings 1975-2004
    - 1975-1976 (Box 1)
    - 1977-1982, 6 folders (Box 1)
      (includes contents of scrapbook documenting Black English case heard in 1979)
    - 1983-2004, 9 folders (Box 1)
  - Development Committee
    - Correspondence and Planning 2003 (Box 1)
    - Development Strategy 2003 (Box 1)
  - Financial Reports and Statements 1997-2004 (Box 1)
  - Office Management
    - Annual Meeting 1996 (Box 1)
    - Data entry and retrieval system (Box 1)
    - Fundraising (Box 1)
    - Job Descriptions (Box 1)
    - Personnel Policy (Box 1)
    - SAC general information (Box 1)
    - Twenty-fifth Anniversary 2000 (Box 1)
    - United Way funding 1999 (Box 1)
  - Publications
    - Access Denied, 1999 (Box 1)
    - Active Voice, 1976-2002 (Box 1)
    - Administrative Law Quarterly
      - " Mandatory Expulsion Requirements and the Erosion of Educational Opportunity in Michigan," Winter 1998-1999 by Sasha Polakow-Suransky (Box 1)
      - "Zero Tolerance," Summer 1999 by Kenneth Ludwig (Box 1)
    - "All We Need To Know, Educating all of Michigan's children," 1985 (Box 1)
    - "Analysis of Suspension Data for the Ann Arbor School District 1975-76 through 1978-79" (with additional material through 1980-81 (Box 1)
    - " Public Education and Social Change: Advocacy Strategies, Special Education, and Parent Involvement," 1996 (Box 1)
    - SAC fliers (Box 1)
    - "Student's Informational Handbook," 1980 (Box 1)
    - "The Fourth 'R', Student Rights, A Handbook for Michigan Public School Students and Their Families," with correspondence regarding publishing
      - In Arabic (Box 1)
      - In English (Box 1)
      - In Spanish (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Ruth Zweifler, Executive Director 1975-2004
  Ruth Zweifler, Executive Director, 1975-2004 series has eight subseries. The Biographical subseries contains a vita and several published profiles. Two subseries contain articles she wrote and articles that cite Zweifler and her activism in Ann Arbor and in Michigan. Zweifler frequently wrote letters to the editor of various newspapers. These can be found in the Clippings subseries under Administration in chronological order. The Correspondence subseries covers 1978-2003 and reflects the expansion of Zweifler's influence on student advocacy statewide. Staff meetings subseries contains minutes for 1999-2001 that show the effect of funded projects on the staff, expanded to include a part-time staff attorney and grant supported personnel. Topical files contain other material related to her career and achievements.
  - All Kids in School Action Coalition 2004 (Box 2)
  - Articles
    - "The Children Left Behind: How Zero Tolerance Impacts Our Most Vulnerable Youth," Michigan Journal of Race & Law Fall 2002 (Box 2)
    - " Student Advocacy: Protecting the Unprotected," Inter Alia, vol. 27, no. 3, Summer, 1989 (Box 2)
    - Viewpoints and Opinions (Box 2)
    - " Zeroing in on School Violence," Bryn Mawr Alumnae Bulletin, Winter, 1999 (Box 2)
  - Biographical (Box 2)
  - Citations of RZ in articles
    - "Catch Them Before They Fall," Teaching Tolerance, Fall 2000 published by Southern Poverty Law Center (Box 2)
    - " Zero Tolerance," Hour Detroit, September, 2001 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence
    - 1978-1985 (Box 2)
    - 1988-1996 (Box 2)
    - 1997-1998 (Box 2)
    - 1999-2004 (Box 2)
  - Mack Open School Parents' Meeting 2000 (Box 2)
  - Staff Meetings August 1999-April, 2001 (Box 2)
  - Topical
    - Awards Received (Box 2)
    - Leslie Harrington, New Director 2004 (Box 2)
    - Marcene Root 2001 (Box 2)
    - Nomination for Leadership for a Changing World Award 2003 (Box 2)
- Program
  The Program series contains seven subseries. The Casework subseries includes information on the primary activity SAC: student advocacy casework. There were several large cases involving entire school districts: Baldwin and Fennville which are documented here. In the beginning, SAC dealt mainly with individual student cases. There is information in this series including forms, summaries and statistics. The Lawyers' Committee subseries includes information on its creation, minutes, and a topical subseries. The Expulsion Data Collection Project was one of their major activities. The committee also dealt with zero tolerance and 504 policies, among others. The Volunteer subseries contains two training manuals, written twenty-three years apart, reflecting changes in techniques over the decades. Volunteers were recruited and trained to support the student and involved parents to find a resolution to school problems, often stemming from suspension or expulsion. The Website development subseries includes copies of pages from the site as it was accessed on August 10, 2004 at http://www.studentadvocacycenter.org. The website made available sample letters, forms, Attorney Listserv, and Quick Guides for many different types of appeals to school districts.
  - Casework
    - Baldwin Community Schools, Bussing issue 1989-1991, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Case Evaluation 2003-2004 (Box 2)
    - Edison Oakland Public School Academy 2003 (Box 2)
    - Fennville Public Schools 1990-1992
      - Correspondence 1990-1992 (Box 2)
      - FOIA response 1992 (Box 2)
    - Huron High School (Box 2)
    - Intake form (Box 2)
    - Pioneer High School (Box 2)
    - Reports and Statistics 1997-2004 (Box 2)
    - Summary cases 1999, 2000 (Box 2)
    - Summary narrative 1994 (Box 2)
    - Suspension statistics 1975-1981 (Box 2)
    - Van Buren Public Schools 1997 (Box 2)
  - Lawyer's Committee 1999-2002
    - Creation 1999 (Box 2)
    - Minutes 1999-2002, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Topical
      - Child Find (Box 2)
        (includes overview of Special Education Laws)
      - Expulsion Data Collection Project
        - Collected Data (Box 3)
        - Correspondence (Box 3)
        - Final Report, "Michigan Public Schools Expulsion Data Academic Year 1999-2000" (Box 3)
        - FOIA requests
          - 1998-1999, 5 folders (Box 3)
          - 2000-2001, 2 folders (Box 3)
          - 2002 Alternative Schools, 3 folders (Box 3)
          - 2002-2003, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - NCAS Committee
    - Zero Tolerance Position Paper 1998 (Box 3)
    - African American Parent/Student Organizing Project 2003 (Box 3)
  - Project Re-Enroll 1999 (Box 3)
  - Project Stylus/SOAR 1998-1999
    - Parent's Group meetings 2000-2001 (Box 3)
    - Stay Put letters (Box 3)
    - Zero Tolerance
      - Case Studies (Box 3)
      - Comparative school discipline study, 15 states 2000 (Box 3)
      - Position of SAC 2000 (Box 3)
  - Volunteers
    - Advocate Training Manual 1976 (Box 3)
    - Orientation Manual 2000 (Box 3)
    - Positions 2000 (Box 3)
  - Website development 1999, 4 folders (Box 3)
- Grants
  Grants and Fundraising series includes both funded and unfunded applications, as well as other materials related to fundraising and cultivating relations with donors. Researchers should look at the grant applications for summary descriptions of SAC and its activities. The Background subseries includes concepts that SAC used in grant applications and a list of funded grants with descriptions. Grants funded include: SOAR, Community Impact, a pass through grant to the Women's Empowerment Project of Monroe, Active Voices of Youth, and Raise a Strong Voice for Children, submitted and funded from 1999 through 2003. These grants demonstrate that SAC was able to form partnerships with Michigan State University and its Institute for Children, Youth, and Family, the Michigan State Bar Foundation, and others, with the purpose of extending their advocacy services throughout Michigan. Student Opportunities and Alternative Resources (SOAR) subseries includes project evaluations and information about STYLUS that, as an outgrowth of SOAR, continued to function within the Washtenaw County ISD. Active Voice of Youth subseries contains the program for a Youth Leadership Conference in September, 2001. The subseries, Raise a Strong Voice for Children Legal Advocacy Project, includes information on the partnership with the University of Michigan Law School and SAC to create an advocacy agenda to be implemented by a staff attorney and volunteer law students. The Michigan State Bar Foundation funded the first year with an Access to Justice grant to address educational equity issues and then continued a second year of funding. The subseries includes the year end report for 2001-2002 by the Project Director/Staff Attorney, Elsa Shartsis. This report documents the losses incurred by SAC in the February 19, 2002 fire in which SAC lost furnishings, equipment, and most of its files, supplies, and reference books. The report outlines the accomplishments of the Project Director and reflects the increasing professionalism of the SAC staff and volunteers. The 2003 grant application evidences SAC's partnership with the University of Michigan Law School and the Michigan Poverty Law Program. SAC's goal was to build a framework for systematic legal advocacy and an attorney network for low-income students and their families. SAC wanted to push beyond non-legal advocacy.
  - Action Plan to Keep Children in School Project, Unitarian Universalist Funding Program 1996-1997 (Box 4)
  - Active Voices of Youth, W. K. Kellogg Foundation 2001
    - Correspondence (Box 4)
    - Proposal and Plans (Box 4)
    - Youth Leadership Conference September 29, 2001, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Ann Arbor Community Development Department 2001-2004 (Box 4)
  - Ann Arbor Friends 2002-2003 (Box 4)
  - Ann Arbor Polaris Foundation 2001-2003 (Box 4)
  - Application for 7th Annual Nonprofit Excellence Award, Nonprofit Enterprise at Work 2002 (Box 4)
  - Background information for applications (Box 4)
  - A Case for Private Giving in Support of the Student Advocacy Center (Box 4)
  - Cheers Grant, Blue Cross/Blue Shield of Michigan (Box 4)
  - City General Fund Allocations, City of Ann Arbor 2002-2004 (Box 4)
  - Community Impact, Ann Arbor Parks and Recreation 2001 (Box 4)
  - Community Impact, CBDG grant 1998-2001 (Box 4)
  - Community Impact, Washtenaw County Children's Services Grant 1999 (Box 4)
  - Constituency Building for Public School Reform, Ford Foundation 1999 (Box 4)
  - Counting All Students, Poverty and Race Research Action Council 2000 (Box 4)
  - Donations to memorials (Box 4)
  - Ford Motor Company 1996-2003 (Box 4)
  - Foundations and individuals, requests for support
    - C. S. Mott Foundation 1996-2002 (Box 4)
    - Edward W. Hazen 1989-2003 (Box 4)
    - Ford Foundation 2002 (Box 4)
    - John S. and James L. Knight Foundation 2003 (Box 4)
    - Michael Moore 2002-2003 (Box 4)
    - Stern Family Fund 2003 (Box 4)
  - Gerald Beckwith Constitutional Liberties fund, Inc. 1994-2004 (Box 4)
  - Grant applications, non-funded proposals
    - Capacity Building Funds, Ann Arbor Area Community Foundation 2003 (Box 4)
    - Capacity Building Funds, City of Ann Arbor 2003 (Box 4)
    - Community Foundation for Southeastern Michigan 2000 (Box 4)
    - Database Installation, Junior League of Ann Arbor 2003 (Box 4)
    - Detroit Edison Foundation 1999 (Box 4)
    - Expanded Advocacy Services of the Educationally Excluded Project, Michigan State Bar Foundation 1991 (Box 4)
    - Latina Girl Initiative, Michigan Women's Foundation 2004 (Box 4)
    - Mobilization for Equity, General Motors 1995 (Box 4)
    - Mothers Mobilizing our Voices for Education, Michigan Women's Foundation 2002 (Box 4)
    - Mutual of America Community Partnership Award 1998, 2002 (Box 4)
    - NCAS /Ford Foundation RFP response 2001 (Box 4)
    - Progressive Technology Project 2000 (Box 4)
    - Project Equal 1999 (Box 4)
    - Rollin Gerstacker Foundation 2003 (Box 4)
    - Rotary Club 1999 (Box 4)
    - Strong Schools and Youth, Washtenaw County 2001 (Box 5)
    - Strong Voice for Children, the Skillman Foundation 1999 (Box 5)
    - UPS Region/District Grant 2002 (Box 5)
    - W. K. Kellogg Foundation 2001
      - Project Meetings and E-Mail (Box 5)
      - Step Up (Box 5)
      - Supporting Academic Success (Box 5)
    - Strong Voice of Youth 2001 (Box 5)
  - I am a Reading Machine Program, Ann Arbor Area Foundation 2000 (Box 5)
  - Individual Educational Advocacy Services, Washtenaw County Human Services 2000-2001 (Box 5)
  - Jackson Income Use Fund, First Unitarian Universalist Church 1999-2003 (Box 5)
  - Jackson Social Welfare Fund, First Unitarian Universalist Church 2001 (Box 5)
  - McGregor Fund Application 2001 (Box 5)
  - Michigan Bar Foundation 1996-2004 (Box 5)
  - Mobilization for Equity Project 1994-1998, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Model Cities Health Center 2001 (Box 5)
  - Monitoring Equal Education Opportunities, Racial Justice Collaborative Fund 2003 (Box 5)
  - Other records related to grants, fundraising, and spending (Box 5)
  - Outreach Program, Washtenaw County, Human Services and Children's Well Being 2004 (Box 5)
  - Pfizer Global Research and Development 2001-2002 (Box 5)
  - Picnic Fundraiser (includes photos) 2001 (Box 5)
  - Positive Action Center, Black United Fund 1996 (Box 5)
  - Pre-proposal to the Annie E. Casey Foundation 1995 (Box 5)
  - Project Equal, C.S. Mott Foundation 2000 (Box 5)
  - Project FOCUS, Michigan State University 2003 (Box 5)
  - Project Phoenix, Interfaith Council of Congregations 2003 (Box 5)
  - Raise a Strong Voice for Children Legal Advocacy Project, Michigan State Bar Foundation 2000-2004
    - Concept draft 2000 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence 2001-2004 (Box 5)
    - Grant extension application 2003-2004, 2004-2005, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Project Meetings and E-Mail 2003 (Box 5)
    - Year-end reports 2003-2004 (Box 5)
  - W.K. Kellogg Foundation, Multiple Projects 1998-2001 (Box 5)
  - Richner and Richner, LLC, Fundraising Consulting 2003 (Box 6)
  - Rollin Gerstacker Foundation 2002 (Box 6)
  - Strong Intertwined Links: Education and Community Together, Ann Arbor Housing Commission 1998 (Box 6)
  - Student Opportunities and Alternative Resources (SOAR), W. K. Kellogg Foundation 1999, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - United Way
    - Campaign Designations 1996-2000 (Box 6)
    - Combined Federal Campaign 1998-2002 (Box 6)
    - Funding Request 2003-2004 (Box 6)
    - State Employee Combined Campaign 1997-2004 (Box 6)
    - Chronological
      - 1997-2005, 8 folders (Box 6)
  - Women's Empowerment Project of Monroe, Children's Trust Fund 2001 (Box 6)
  - Youth in Action, MSU Families and Communities Together 2001-2001 (Box 6)
- Digital Materials